All right.
בוקר טוב *Boker tov* everybody.
Today's דף daf *daf* is ק"ט *Kuf Tes*, 109, and we pick
up
here- oh what's happening here- hold on. All right. Today's דף *daf*
is ק"ט *Kuf Tes*, 109, and we pick up here at the
very bottom of ק"ח עמוד ב' *Kuf Chet amud bet*, the משנה
Mishna *mishna*. It's actually these דפים *dapim* are very well laid out
that like they end at the right before the next משנה Mishna
*mishna*. All right, so we pick up the very last line of
ק"ח עמוד ב' *Kuf Chet amud bet*. We're now dealing with the
seven rulings of אדמון Admon *Admon*. So let's take a look.
הפוסק מעות לחתנו *Haposake ma'os l'chasno*, now back to marriage issues. A
person basically makes a deal, the whole idea that you know the
father-in-laws would make a deal with their son-in-laws that they'd sit and
learn and they'd support them, well this doesn't talk about sitting and
learn, but it does talk about a deal. Okay, so somebody made
basically a deal with his son-in-law: you marry my daughter, I will
go out and give you $10,000 or whatever it is he agreed
to. ופשט לו את הרגל *u'pashat lo es haregel* and then he
stuck his foot out at the guy like this image of like
sticking out and let- like he'll trip over his leg. But basically
means like sort of like he you know he's reneging on the
deal. It's some idiom. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says maybe it means like
you stick out your you know foot to somebody, your shoe and
you say go clean you know the bottom of my shoe or
something like that. No, no. The father-in-law basically is now you know
he's acting in a disrespectful way, but it's not about the disrespect.
It's basically just means that he's reneging on the deal.
Did he marry the daughter?
No, well, he did
קידושין *kiddushin* apparently and not נישואין *nisuin*. Okay, so what's the story?
ופשט לו את הרגל *u'pashat lo es haregel*. He's kicking him in
the תחת *tuchus*. תשב עד שתלבין ראשה teshev ad she-talvin rosha, *Teshev
ad shetyalbin roshah*. So this guy has no responsibility to do anything,
this son-in-law who did קידושין *kiddushin* and not נישואין *nisuin*. It's like,
you don't want to give me the $10,000 you promised? I'll marry
her? You don't want to give it to me? I'm not even
going to agree to divorce her. So by the way you possibly
have an עגונה *agunah*. It wasn't על תנאי *al tnai*. So now
there is an interesting question in תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* which is was
the condition binding or not? Right, remember the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* before
that when they make a deal and then they immediately get, you
know, get married right afterwards and then הן הן הדברים הנקנים באמירה
*Hein Hein Ha-Devarim Haniknim Ba-Amira*, that makes even the oral contract binding?
So תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says two interpretations. One is it's not a
binding contract because that was only when they married right after the
deal was struck. Here they made the deal, like a week later
they got married, so it's just an oral agreement, it's not binding.
But nevertheless since that was the understanding and the condition,
so on the one hand you can't go ahead and sue me
for the $10,000 because it wasn't a binding contract. On the other
hand, the son-in-law says you can't force me to go ahead and
do נישואין *nisuin*. You know, so I can't get the money out
of you because it wasn't a binding contract, but on the other
hand that was my understanding and that was our agreement and I'm
not going to go ahead and do נישואין *nisuin*. That's one way
of reading it, that the contract wasn't binding. The other way of
reading it was that the contract actually or another way is that
the contract was binding, but it would only be binding when actually
it finally ended in נישואין *nisuin*. Okay, so therefore you know, and
so anyway that somehow it's still not binding yet. Anyway, one version
of it is that it's not binding and the other version is
that it is binding. So if it is binding, why doesn't the
חתן *chosson* just basically sue the guy? Okay, so basically says because
he's not interested, either the guy's no money so suing the guy
won't do any good, or he's not interested in having to deal
with all the court issues of suing the guy, okay. But the
bottom line is that even if it's a binding contract, to some
degree the father-in-law is making his life very difficult. He's not just
willfully keeping up his end of the bargain. Okay, but it might
be easier to understand the more simple sense of this משנה Mishnah
*mishna* is that it's somehow not binding and he's reneging. It was
an implicit understanding, he's reneging and therefore what's- what's left to the
son-in-law? All that's left to the son-in-law is that he can basically
say, I'm going to refuse to get married until you decide to
keep up your end of the bargain. Okay, but the interesting thing
also is that well, then just give her a גט get. *get*.
Why is he not giving her a גט get, *get*? So unfortunately
it might be an indication of you know of an early you
know fact of using the גט get, *get* as leverage, right? He's
got a lot of control over this woman. She's stuck, she can't
marry anybody else and he's refusing to marry her. And it sounds
like he's using that as a certain degree of leverage. Okay, so
that's what it says, תשב עד שתלבין ראשה *teshev ad shetyalbin roshah*.
Let the hair on her head grow white. The father is reneging
on his deal, the חתן *chosson's* entitled to do that.
So he's basically keep her as an עגונה *agunah*.
That is essentially what it's saying. אדמון אומר Admon omer, *Admon omer*,
אדמון Admon. *Admon* says, יכולה היא שתאמר yechola hi she-tomar, לו *yechola
hee shetomar lo*, she can say, אילו אני פסקתי לעצמי *ilu ani
pasakti l'atzmi*, if I had made the deal... If I had made
the deal and I was reneging on the deal, then אשב עד
שתלבין ראשי, then fine, then I would be willing to sit until
the hair of my head grew white because I was reneging on
the deal. So, you know, you're entitled to go ahead and, you
know, pull your שטיק, shtick,
which by the way is also troubling, you know, because it basically
says, well, if somebody did something to me, then that gives me
license to go ahead and, you know, do something back in terms
again of that like sort of whole, you know, whatever. Anyway, but
he says, look, at least I'd understand it if it was me
who had
had reneged. אבא פסק, abba pasak, but it's my father that made
the deal and my father that reneged. מה אני יכולה לעשות, ma
ani yechola la'asot, it's not... I'm not to blame. או כנוס או
פטור, o kenos o patur, make up your mind, either do me
כנוס kenos or give me a גט. get Okay, I'm sorry you
won't get the money, but you can't hold me hostage. Okay, I
didn't do anything wrong.
You hear אדמון Admon. setting precedent right in the משנה Mishnah of
pushing back on... Exactly, exactly.
אמר רבן גמליאל רואה אני את דברי אדמון,
amar
Rabban Gamliel
ro'eh ani et divrei Admon, I see the position of אדמון.
Admon That sounds like רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, you know, we had
that whole...
No, before was רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan דכאי Zakkai who was... רבי
יוחנן בן זכאי Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai who was agreeing with חנן,
Chanan, and here we have רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel who's agreeing with
אדמון. Admon Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this: מתניתין דלא
כי האי תנא, matnitin d'lo ki hai tanna, our משנה that frames
the issue that the father made the deal is not like the
following תנא. tanna. דתניא, d'tanya, we learned in a ברייתא, braita, אמר
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, amar Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda, לא נחלקו אדמון
וחכמים על הפוסק מעות לחתנו ופשט לו את הרגל, lo nechelku Admon
v'Chachamim al ha-posek ma'ot l'chattano u-pashat lo et ha-regel, the אדמון Admon
and חכמים Chachamim do not disagree when it was the father that
made the deal with the son-in-law and the father basically reneged, שיכולה
היא שתאמר, she-yechola hi she-tomar, that she is entitled to say, look,
I didn't make the deal. אבא פסק, abba pasak, פסק, pasak, אבא
פסק עלי, abba pasak alai, my father made the deal, מה אני
יכולה לעשות, ma ani yechola la'asot, why is it my fault? על
מה נחלקו, al ma nechelku, what did they debate? על שפסקה היא
על עצמה, al she-paska hi al atzma, when she herself made the
deal, שחכמים אומרים, she-Chachamim omrim, in that case, the חכמים Chachamim say,
look, you made the deal, you reneged, תשב עד שתלבין ראשה,
rather, you know, you brought it on yourself, so the hair here
could go white because he doesn't have to do anything. אדמון אומר,
Admon omer, and אדמון Admon says no, even when she made the
deal and she reneged, יכולה היא שתאמר, she could say, look, סבורה
הייתי שאבא נותן עלי, svura hayiti she-abba noten alai, I, yes, I
made the deal, but I thought my father would be the one
to write the check. ועכשיו שאין אבא נותן עלי, v'achshav she-ein abba
noten alai, and now, but you
know, my father is not writing the check, מה אני יכולה לעשות,
ma ani yechola la'asot, it's out of my hands. I don't have
any money. I mean, I made the deal, but ultimately the not
fulfilling it is out of my hands. או כנוס או פטור, o
kenos o patur, it's out of my control and you can't go
ahead and let me suffer for self and, you know, if you
need... want to give me a גט, get, give me a גט,
get. but at least, you know, set me free. אמר רבן גמליאל
רואה אני את דברי אדמון, amar Rabban Gamliel ro'eh ani et divrei
Admon, I see the words of אדמון Admon, in that case. Okay,
so that's even more, you know, how he is not entitled to
use the גט get and to hold her hostage. דתניא, d'tanya, we
learned in a ברייתא... braita...
well, the גט, Get yeah.
תנא במה דברים אמורים, tanna bameh devarim amurim, when is all this
true? גדולה, gdola, she's an adult. אבל בקטנה, aval b'ktana, if she's
a minor, כופין, kofin, then you would actually force. So the גמרא
Gemara says, כופין למי, kofin le-mi, who are we going to force
in the case where she was a minor?
אילימא לאב, ilima l'av, you'd force the father to pay
up, okay, השתא ומה גדולה, hashtah u-ma gdola, it doesn't make sense.
If she's a minor, then she's less bound by her agreement than
if she's an adult. Why would you more force the father to
fulfill his end or her end of the bargain if she's a
minor? אלא אמר רבא, ela amar Rava, כופין לבעל ליתן גט, kofin
l'ba'al liten get,
you actually would force the husband. If she was a minor according
to this version of the ברייתא, braita, right? The only reason that
basically,
you know, that she's bound is because this ברייתא braita says that
if the father makes the agreement and the father reneged and it's
not her fault, you basically force the guy to give a גט.
The only time that it might change that there's a debate is
if she made the agreement and she backs out, right? So in
that case, here we're saying even that debate would only be when
she was an adult. But if she was a minor and she
made the agreement, then it's not really a binding agreement. She's a
minor. So you also can't hold her hostage. Okay, so according to
this ברייתא, braita, nobody...
everybody agrees the husband will be forced to give a גט assuming
he refuses to marry her. He'll be forced to do something either
if it was the father that made the agreement, so she can't
suffer as a result, or she was a minor when she made
the agreement, so also she's not really bound. The whole debate is
that she was an adult when she made the agreement and she's
reneging. And even in that case, אדמון Admon, says you cannot hold
her hostage. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, אמר רבי יצחק בר אלעזר משמיה דחזקיה, amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar
Elazar mishmei d'Chizkiya, כל מקום שאמר רבן גמליאל רואה אני את דברי
אדמון, kol makom she-amar Rabban Gamliel ro'eh ani et divrei Admon, wherever
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says I see the position of אדמון, Admon
הלכה כמותו, halacha kemoto, we rule like him. Now the two things
that חנן Chanan had said, רבי יוחנן בן זכאי Rabbi Yochanan ben
Zakkai said רואה אני את דברי חנן, ro'eh ani et divrei Chanan,
and that was so the whole two things that חנן Chanan had
said, he had somebody else, רבי יוחנן בן זכאי, Rabbi Yochanan ben
Zakkai, you know, affirming it. Here by אדמון, Admon it's only... אדמון
Admon is going to say seven things, and רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
only affirms it in two of them or in three of them,
the first three. This is the third of them. After this, the
next four things that אדמון Admon, is going to say, רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel is not going to say, "I see his position." So
what we're saying is that we rule like, we rule like אדמון
Admon only in these first three things that we just said, okay,
the whole thing about the about the jars of oil, the other
thing we said about the, you know, why just because I'm male
I lose out, although תוספות Tosafot says that really wasn't a הלכה,
halacha, that was really just he was being astounded. And this last
thing about that you are now allowed to hold the woman hostage
even if the deal is not being fulfilled, okay. So those are
the things we rule like אדמון, Admon the next four that אדמון
Admon. is going to say we don't necessarily rule like him. All
right, so כל מקום שאמר רבן גמליאל רואה אני את דברי אדמון
הלכה כמותו, Kol makom she-amar Rabban Gamliel ro-eh ani et divrei Admon
halacha kemoto, אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן, Amar lei Rava le-Rav Nachman,
so Rava says to Rav Nachman: אפילו בברייתא? Afilu be-beraita? Would that
apply even to the ברייתא’s beraita version of this debate? Right, the
משנה’s version of this debate is that the father backs out, the
ברייתא’s beraita version is אדמון Admon, says even if she’s backing out,
you can’t hold her hostage. Okay, so would it even go according
to the ברייתא’s beraita version of this debate? אמר ליה, Amar lei,
he said back to him: מי קאמינא במשנה? Mi ka-amina be-Mishnah? Did
I say wherever רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says in the משנה we
rule like him? No. בכל מקום שאמר רבן גמליאל קאמינא. Be-chol makom
she-amar Rabban Gamliel ka-amina. I said wherever רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says
we go like אדמון. Admon So the ברייתא beraita is also a
place where רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says we go like אדמון, Admon
so we rule like אדמון Admon even in the ברייתא’s beraita version,
and therefore even if she's the one that makes the deal and
she's the one that's backing out, he is not allowed to hold
her hostage.
Okay. אמר רבי זירא אמר רבה בר ירמיה: Amar Rabbi Zeira amar
Rabbah bar Yirmeyah: בב' דברים שאמר חנן, Be-vei devarim she-amar Chanan,
הלכה כיוצא בו. halacha kiyotzei vo. We rule like him in similar—now
there's a question what the word כיוצא בו kiyotzei vo here means.
You know, I would have thought and תוספות Tosafot says what it
means is we rule like him in similar cases as well, not
only the exact case he's talking about, but we sort of derive
a principle and we apply that principle to similar cases. רש"י Rashi
says כיוצא בו kiyotzei vo means that the one who also affirms
it, meaning that רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yohanan ben Zakkai says,
"Oh, I like what חנן Chanan said." Or רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
says, "I like what אדמון Admon says." So the voice of רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and the voice of רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban
Yohanan ben Zakkai are the כיוצא בו's, kiyotzei vo are the ones
that are having similar positions. Okay, so again to read what this
would say, it would be the
following: בב' דברים שאמר חנן, Be-vei devarim she-amar Chanan,
the two things that חנן Chanan says, הלכה כיוצא בו, halacha kiyotzei
vo, either means we rule like him and we apply it to
related cases, we actually extract the principles of it and we, you
know, we're guided by that principle, that's the way תוספות Tosafot reads
it, which is powerful to say we don't just leave it to
the concrete case, we actually go by it as a principle. Or
the way רש"י Rashi reads it is the two things חנן Chanan
says, we rule like the one who affirmed it, so since only
someone affirmed it, well yeah, but by חנן Chanan it was the
whole two. So since רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yohanan ben Zakkai
affirmed the two, so we rule like both of those cases, but
the reason is because it was affirmed. Okay. שבעה דברים שאמר אדמון,
Shiva devarim she-amar Admon, the seven things that אדמון Admon said, אין
הלכה כיוצא בו, ein halacha kiyotzei vo,
which either means like we do not use it as a general
rule is the way תוספות Tosafot would say it, or would mean
like we don't go like the one who affirmed it. Okay. So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Well, let's see how the
גמרא Gemara spells it out. מאי קאמר? Mai ka-amar? What are you
saying? אילימא הכי קאמר: Elima hachi ka-amar: שני דברים שאמר חנן הלכה
כמותו וכיוצא בו. Shenei devarim she-amar Chanan halacha kemoto u-kiyotzei vo. The
two things that חנן Chanan said we rule like him in those
cases and—and the one—either again and the one who affirmed it, which
is basically just redundant here, or and apply it to similar cases.
Okay, right, exactly, because it makes it sound like two separate points.
ושבעה דברים שאמר
אדמון, U-shiva devarim she-amar Admon, but the seven things that אדמון Admon
said, אין הלכה כמותו, ein halacha kemoto, we don't rule like him,
ולא כיוצא בו, ve-lo kiyotzei vo, and we don't rule either like
him in other related cases, or again that's תוספות Tosafos say, or
רש"י Rashi say and we don't rule like the one who affirmed
his position. Okay, so if anyway that basically means we totally reject
everything אדמון Admon. said. How could you say that? והאמר רבי יצחק
בן אלעזר משמיה דחזקיה: Ve-ha-amar Rabbi Yitzchak ben Elazar mishmeih de-Chizkiyah: כל
מקום שאמר רבן גמליאל רואה אני את דברי אדמון הלכה כמותו. Kol
makom she-amar Rabban Gamliel ro-eh ani et divrei Admon halacha kemoto. We
know that at least in the first three things that אדמון Admon
says that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel affirms, we do rule like him,
so you cannot read that earlier statement to say we completely reject
אדמון. Admon, אלא הכי קאמר, Ela hachi ka-amar, fine, here's how to
read it. שני דברים שאמר חנן הלכה כמותו וכיוצא בו. Shenei devarim
she-amar Chanan halacha kemoto u-kiyotzei vo. The two things חנן Chanan says
we rule like him and כיוצא בו, kiyotzei vo, we rule like
him and again, and like it in similar cases, or and we
rule like the one who affirmed his position, which is just being
redundant. שבעה דברים שאמר אדמון, Shiva devarim she-amar Admon, the seven things
that אדמון Admon says, אין הלכה כיוצא בו. ein halacha kiyotzei vo.
We don't rule—so let me first read it תוספות's Tosafos. way. We
don't rule like it in similar cases. הכמותו הלכה בכולהו, Ha-kemoto halacha
be-chulhu,
which would suggest that in terms of the concrete cases he's dealing
with, we rule like him in all seven. Okay, but that can't
be. והאמר רבי יצחק בן אלעזר משמיה דחזקיה: Ve-ha-amar Rabbi Yitzchak ben
Elazar mishmeih de-Chizkiyah: כל מקום שאמר רבן גמליאל רואה אני את דברי
אדמון הלכה כמותו. Kol makom she-amar Rabban Gamliel ro-eh ani et divrei
Admon halacha kemoto.
So wherever he affirms אדמון, Admon we rule like him. אמר אין,
Amar in, only in the places where he affirms אדמון Admon we
rule like him, לא אמר לא, lo amar lo, where he doesn't
affirm אדמון Admon we don't rule like him. So you can't say
we rule like אדמון Admon in all seven cases, even in the
concrete cases. because we know we only rule like him in the
three cases. אלא הכי קאמר, Ela hachi ka’amar, here’s what it means:
שני דברים שאמר חנן הלכה כמותו וחיוצא בו. Shnei devarim she-amar Chanan
halachah kemoto ve-hayotzei bo. By חנן Chanan we rule like him and
in the related cases. שבעה דברים שאמר אדמון, Shiva devarim she-amar Admon,
the seven things that אדמון Admon says, יש מהם שהלכה כמותו וחיוצא
בו, yesh mehem she-halachah kemoto ve-hayotzei bo,
sometimes we rule like him both concretely and in related cases, ויש
מהם שאין הלכה כמותו וחיוצא בו, ve-yesh mehem she-ein halachah kemoto ve-hayotzei
bo,
and there are things that we don’t rule like him or in
the concrete or in the related cases. What are they? וכל מקום
שאמר רבן גמליאל רואה אני את דברי אדמון הלכה כמותו, Ve-chol makom
she-amar Rabban Gamliel ro’eh ani et divrei Admon halachah kemoto, where רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says we rule like אדמון Admon we go like
him and we apply it not only to those concrete cases but
to related
cases, ואינך לא, ve-inach lo, and in the others we don’t rule
like him or like the related case. So basically it completely reshapes
this statement to make it fit into the frame that we had
before. The frame that we had before is we only go like
him in three cases. This statement one way or another sounded like
we don’t go like him at all, and the גמרא Gemara sort
of reshaped it to be exactly what we had said until now.
So the way תוספות Tosafos reads it, what it’s just telling you
is we rule like חנן Chanan in both of his cases, we
rule like אדמון Admon in the first three. Not only do we
rule like them in their concrete, specific cases, but we abstract a
general principle and we rule similarly in other cases. That’s the way
תוספות. Yeah, for חנן Chanan too it says וחיוצא בו. ve-hayotzei bo.
That’s the way תוספות reads it. Again, the way רש"י reads it
is a way more complicated read, but basically it was a way
of saying we rule like him in the cases where there was
somebody who affirmed what he said, when it was a וחיוצא בו.
ve-hayotzei bo. When there was someone who affirmed like he said, we
rule like him. When there wasn’t someone who affirmed like he said,
we don’t rule like him. Yes, Dov?
Did you ever say anything about when אדמון Admon lived, like what
generation?
Yeah, no, I don’t know, I did not. I’m sure somebody could,
Charlie or someone.
Charlie is
checking it up in his iPhone. I don’t know. All right. It’s
somewhat early. I mean, you have רבי יוחנן בן זכאי Rabbi Yochanan
ben Zakkai affirming him, so he’s got to be somewhat early. Okay.
While the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash was still around.
Well, רבי יוחנן בן זכאי.
Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai.
Yeah, exactly. רבי יוחנן בן זכאי Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai was at
least the next generation, so yeah. And it’s, you know, so anyway,
okay. So, but yeah, I think it’s important to have that historical
framing. Okay. העובר על השדה. Ha-over al ha-sadeh.
Now, again, not with the incessant where we’re weaving back and forth
between כתובות Kesuvos related cases. There are דיני ממונות, dinei mamonus, you
know, that’s why it’s שני דייני גזירות shnei dayanei gezeiros because they’re
all like דיני ממונות dinei mamonus types of cases. העובר על השדה.
Ha-over al ha-sadeh. I basically Charlie there sold the field to Michael,
and I’m saying, Michael, that field you bought that Charlie sold you,
that was actually my field. Charlie was misrepresenting himself, he really did
not own that field, he had seized it when I was away
on a trip. Okay? He was presenting himself as the owner. You
know, that’s Charlie for you. Okay. That’s really my field. And I’m
going to try to go ahead and bring witnesses and prove that
it was my field and that Charlie never really established legitimate ownership.
And I would win the case. I have the evidence on my
side. There’s only one little problem. That document of sale that Charlie
sold the field to you, I’m one of the witnesses on that
document. Okay? העובר
על השדה וחתם עליה בעד.
Ha-over al
ha-sadeh ve-chatam aleha be-ed.
And I’m one of the witnesses, I’m on that document. אדמון Admon,
אומר, אדמון Admon says, I do not lose my rights to prove
that that’s my field. השני נוח לי והראשון קשה הימנו. Ha-sheni no’ach
li ve-ha-rishon kasheh himenu. I can say, yeah, you know why? Because
Charlie, there’s a reason he’s a thief and a thug, because everybody
is afraid to go up against him, and he’s going to send
his henchmen against me if I try to bring him to court.
So I wanted him to sell the field to you so I
could retrieve it from you. Now you’re going to have to go
try to get your money back from Charlie. Good luck. So that’s
why just because I signed the document does not prove that I’m
conceding it’s not my field. I could actually make that statement.
Is that not a problem to do that?
What to stay... Oh, that I am causing
you not being able to... or me shifting the problem onto me.
Right, that I am basically... I right, I’m basically tricking you into
throwing your money down away, you know, risking your money.
Right, but I don’t have to say it that way. Why can’t
it be, listen, he extorted me. I really had to.
Okay, so that could be. But I was thinking that too. Like
Charlie would come to me and say, you know, I want to
make sure that... right, exactly. I stole that field from you, you’re
not going to do anything. I’m holding a gun to your head
and now you’re going to sign the document and it’s going to
be... Right, so I don’t know why he can’t, but maybe because
that would have required maybe I don’t know more evidence or something.
But if he’s got a gun to his head?
Right, because what... right. Well, that’s the point. That’s the חידוש chiddush
of אדמון's Admon statement. Right, if I were claiming that I was
forced, right, that’s like a harder claim to substantiate. If I’m claiming...
I don’t have to claim that Charlie was doing anything to get
me to sign the document. I just willingly said, I heard Charlie
was signing it, I wanted to make that happen. I came running
to sign the document because it was going to be easier for
me. So yes, you could say that I’m claiming that I was
forced, but that’s a... but that’s a harder claim to substantiate. Here
I’m just saying, no, I just completely did it willingly and here’s
why. Okay, now I don’t know, that’s a good question. Maybe it’s
not מותר. mutar. for me to do, but anyway but at least
אביי Abaye says I could make that claim. וחכמי אומרין Vechachamei omrin
and the חכמים Chachamim say איבד את זכותו. ibad et zchuto. I'm
sorry, if you signed a document as a witness that was saying
that it was Charlie's field that he was selling to Michael, then
you are implicitly conceding that it was Charlie's. Again, if you could
prove you were forced, that's a different story. And here, by the
way, we don't rule like אדמון, Admon we rule like the חכמים,
Chachamim, which makes sense. עשאה סימן לאחר, Asaa siman leachar, איבד את
זכותו. ibad et zchuto. Let's say that, here's a case where even
אדמון would agree, okay, which is that Charlie is not selling this
field to you, Michael. He's selling the field one field over, okay?
He's selling field B to you, not field A. And when he's
describing the boundaries of field B, on it it says: Field B
has its north limit is field C, its west limit is field
D, its south limit is field E, and its, what was I
left over, its east limit, its east edge is field A, and
all of those are my other fields, and I'm selling you this
field B in the middle. So he was using the field I
say he stole from me as a way of showing you what
the borders are of the field he's selling to you. But in
that document, he was claiming that that field is his, right? Field
A is his. You got the point? So therefore, I have no
reason I would have signed that document. It's not making it any
easier for me to retrieve field A. In passing, in that document,
it's claiming that field A belongs to Charlie. Okay, but he's not
selling field A to you, he's selling the neighboring field to you.
Okay, so he's just using it as a boundary marker.
As a boundary marker. Exactly. Exactly.
And so why, the fact that I am signing that document, it
doesn't benefit me at all to sign that document, and that document
is saying that that field is Charlie's. So there, even אדמון agrees
that I have no claim, and that basically I've lost any right
to claim it was my field. Okay, but anyway, but the debate
is when he is selling it to Michael, and can I say,
yes, I signed it because I would rather go to court with
Michael. Okay, אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, says אביי, Abaye, לא שנו אלא
עד. Lo shanu ela ed. When is there a debate? That's when
I signed as a witness. Or not even a debate. When is
it that there are cases where my signature concedes that it is
Charlie's field? When I'm signing as a witness. אבל דיין, Aval dayan,
but let's say it was this same document that Charlie had sold
the field to Michael, and basically he was selling a field that
I'm claiming as mine, and the document came, you know, here before
me, Dov, and David, and we needed to validate the signatures. Okay,
so we went ahead, we looked at the signatures, we said, yes,
we recognize the signatures on these documents, we gave it our stamp,
and we validated the שטר. shtar. Does that, and in the document
it said that Charlie is selling a particular field to you, and
then I claim that field actually was mine, it wasn't Charlie's. Does
the fact that I was part of the signing of the validating
of the signatures, does that become a concession, an admission that it
wasn't my field?
It makes it worse, doesn't it?
I validated the signatures on a document that said that it was
Charlie's field. Why shouldn't that be an admission that it's not my
field?
I think it is.
So the גמרא Gemara. says not. אבל דיין לא איבד את זכותו.
Aval dayan lo ibad et zchuto. If you were a judge to
give a to endorse the signatures, you do not implicitly concede what's
being stated in the document. Why? דתני רבי חייא, Detani Rabbi Chiyya,
because רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya taught, אין העדים חותמים
על השטר אלא אם כן קראוהו. Ein haedim chotmim al hashtar ela
im ken kerauhu. Witnesses cannot sign a document unless they've read it,
because the document is attesting to something, and they have to know
what they're attesting to, so they gotta read it before they sign.
אבל הדיינים, Aval hadayanim, but judges, yeah, right, yeah, but judges who
are being asked to endorse the signatures on a document, חותמים אף
על פי שלא קראוהו. chotmim af al pi shelo kerauhu. We don't
have to read it. All we have to do is attest to
the fact that these are the right signatures. You bring over a
notary public and to get it to give her the notary thing,
she doesn't, I keep saying she because every time I've dealt with
a notary public it's always been a woman, anyway, don't know why,
she or he, anyway, doesn't have to read the document. They just
are testifying that your signatures are your signatures. You should be in
Israel.
You should see what you have to do for a notary in
Israel. I could not believe it. Really? It's like going to
a law firm and reading the whole deal. Really? I thought, oh,
signatures, okay. Oh, no.
You should have told them this גמרא. Gemara Alright, so
therefore, when the notary signs it or the judges sign and validate
the signature, and validate the signature,
there is no implicit attesting to any of the content that is
in the document.
But if you actually were a judge and said I read it
and I disagree, yeah, I mean, I guess.
עשאה סימן לאחר. Asaa siman leachar. Now, if, however, a field was
used as a marker and wasn't being sold to Michael, then even
אדמון agrees that it's an implicit admission. Why else would I have
signed the document?
I didn't understand that case clearly.
In other words, Michael sold a field to Michael, Charlie sold a
field to Michael,
and he said the north boundary of that field is this other
field, we'll call field A. That's the north boundary of the field
I'm selling to you. Field A is the field that I'm claiming
was mine. Charlie stole from me. But Charlie says to Michael, "the
north boundary of the field I'm selling you, Michael, is my other
field, Field A." So he's claiming Field A is his field and
he's using it as a boundary marker for the field he's selling
Michael. And I'm saying it's my field. If I signed the document
of sale, if I was a witness to the document of sale,
then I have conceded that it's Charlie's field. Why else would I
have signed a document of sale in which Charlie is saying that
it's his field if I did not concede that it was his
field? Right. And the only claim is that if I'm signing it
to get the field to change hands, I have an argument why
I wanted it to change hands because it would be easier for
me to take Michael to court.
But here he's used the fine print in that effect.
I know, that's why you gotta be careful what you're reading. Okay.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, says Abaye, לא שנו אלא לאחר, Lo shanu
ela leachar,
that's only if you're selling it to somebody else. Okay, but אבל
לעצמו, Aval le'atzmo,
let's say Charlie is selling me one of his fields, okay, and
Charlie is so like, he's, it's not enough for him to steal
my field, he has to like rub it in. So he's selling
me one of his fields and he's saying the north boundary of
the field I'm selling you is Field A, which is my field.
Okay, the field that I'm saying he stole from me. Okay, so
and I'm and so I basically, so you got it, so Charlie
sold a field to me with a document that basically, you know,
used in it the field I'm saying is mine and he's claiming,
sorry, and he's claiming that that's the boundary of the field he
signs for me.
So the fact,
but okay, why am I participating in that sale and allowing him
to write that in the document unless I was actually conceding that
it was his? So he says in that case, okay, should it
be an admission that it's not yours because why else would you
allow him to write it in the document? So he says no,
actually in that case it's not an admission. Why is it not
an admission? In that case, לא איבד את זכותו, Lo ibad es
zechuso, you do not lose your right. Why not?
One minute, let me just check. One minute, I just want to
check a Rashi just second, one
minute.
Right. Okay, so anyway, so but in that case I did not
lose my right. Why not? Why would I participate in a document
that was using my own field and claiming that it was Charlie's?
דאמר אי לא עבדי ליה הכי, De'amar i lo avdi lei hachi,
if I had not let him do that, הוה לא מזבין לי,
Havah lo mazbin li, he wouldn't have sold me that other field,
right? I was at least, you know, so I would have screwed
up the deal. If I would have said, "no, I refuse to
sign a document that you're using my own field as a boundary
marker and claiming it's yours," so he's said "fine, then I'm not
going to sell you the field." Okay, so I was sort of
like being pressured if I needed that field, he already stole one
field, I want at least have another field to use in its
stead or whatever. I had no choice but to go along with
how he was, what he was doing. Okay, so מאי אית לך
למימר, Mai is lach lemeimar, so what should you say back? Okay,
but if that's why you agreed to it because you needed to
do it so he would sell you the other field, so איבעי
ליה לממסר מודעא, Ibai lei lemimsar moda'a, no, then at least you
should have informed witnesses that you were being forced. Okay, this is
an idea which is called a מודעא, Moda'a, which basically means that
if somebody is holding a gun to your head and forcing
you to enter into a deal or to sign a document or
to do something that is not true, you get witnesses and you
tell them "you should know, I am testifying to you right now
that that deal I'm about to enter into, I am actually doing
it under coercion and under duress" and then later you can produce
those witnesses to try to reverse the deal. So if basically I
felt that I'm buying that field from Charlie, he's using my own
field as a boundary marker, but I really have no choice because
I need to buy the other field from him, then why didn't
I at least tell witnesses that "you should know, I'm going to
be using, you know, buying this document but I'm not really conceding
to what it says in it, I really just don't have any
choice." So if that's your counterclaim, איבעי ליה לממסר מודעא, Ibai lei
lemimsar moda'a, no,
I couldn't see that. Why not? חברך חברא אית ליה, Chavrach chavara
is lei, your friend has a friend, וחברא דחברך חברא אית ליה,
Vechavara dechavrach chavara is lei, and your friend's friend has a friend,
which is the Gemara's way of saying Ben Franklin's line, which is:
three people can keep a secret if two of them are dead.
Okay, so
Ben Franklin.
So, which basically means it's all very nice to do a מודעא,
Moda'a, but I could claim that I won't do a מודעא, Moda'a,
that if I did a מודעא, Moda'a, I would lose the field
because he would eventually find out. Now, of course, if that was
a real concern, you would never be able to do a מודעא,
Moda'a, because the word would get out and whatever, but anyway, but
at least that's enough of a basis for me to say that's
why, you know, don't interpret my signature or don't interpret my using
this document as a concession, I have a reasonable explanation why I
used it. I used the document. I used it because I needed
to buy the field, he wouldn't have sold it to me otherwise,
and I was concerned that I couldn't let other people know. And
since that's a reasonable explanation, my signing on that document is not
interpreted as a losing of my rights and as a concession. Yes.
Can women be witnesses?
No, not in this formal sense. I mean in אשכנז Ashkenaz in
the Middle Ages in the time of the ראשונים Rishonim
they basically for all intents and purposes accepted women as witnesses but
they did it like by sort of saying we're using them as
evidence not as witnesses, you know, by so sort of that type
of a loophole. And the basic difference would be, you know, so
it would be a difference like in terms of like can you
know when you need witnesses in a formal sense like to validate
a wedding or גט or something like that. All right, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
Yes. This is a קשיא Kasha against the מוסר מודעא, Moser Moda'ah,
in other words, right?
In other words, that's a counter-claim. Here's why I was not מוסר
מודעא Moser Moda'ah and here's why you should believe me when I
say that I did not what do you call it that I
that I signed because I really didn't have a choice and that
it really wasn't a concession.
And if I would have got those עדים Eidim it would have
gotten out.
Exactly. Exactly.
And he would have made mincemeat of
me. Exactly.
So that's why I can say that I used my what do
you call it? That's why I can say that I agreed to
use that document even though it basically was using my own field
against me.
I should have gotten עדים Eidim because within two minutes I would
have been vulnerable.
Correct. Okay. So now we have a nice little story.
You want this thing?
No, I have another one. I don't know what that's doing there.
Okay, so now we have another one.
Okay. ההוא דעשה סימן לאחר. Hahu de-asa siman le-acher. So there was
a case exactly like this that a guy signed on a field
and signed on a document and his own field was used as
a סימן Siman for the for the for the other field as
a boundary marker. And the guy in the document was claiming it
was his when this guy, you know, said it was stolen.
עיר ושכיב. E'ar ve-shachiv. Then he challenged it and he died. Okay.
Before he had a chance to actually finally bring the case to
court, right? And so עיר ושכיב. E'ar ve-shachiv. ואוקימא אפוטרופוס. Ve-ukima apitropas.
So then the court appointed an אפוטרופוס, Apitropas, a guardian, you know,
or an executor somebody to represent the orphans in all of their
business dealings, among which is the question about this field that their
now dead father was claiming actually was his.
And he used it as a סימן Siman in another שדה. Sadeh.
Exactly. Exactly. He had right he had forfeited his right by having
signed that document. But now there's an אפוטרופוס Apitropas who's going to
try to argue the case for for the orphans. אתא אפוטרופוס. Ata
apitropas. The אפוטרופוס Apitropas came קמיה דאביי Kamei d'Abaye in front of
אביי. Abaye. אמר ליה אביי Amar leh Abaye said to him and
he brought evidence that the field was stolen that it really belonged
to the heirs, the orphans. אמר ליה אביי Amar leh Abaye said
No, I'm sorry. Your the father you know forfeited the right. עשה
סימן לאחר ואיבד זכותו. Asa siman le-acher ve-ibeid zechuto. He signed on
a document and it was used as a boundary marker and he
implicitly conceded that it wasn't his. So I'm sorry, you know, you
lost the the you know they lost the right, he lost out.
So אמר, Amar, so the אפוטרופוס Apitropas said אי הוי אבוהון דיתמי
קיים Ihavi avuhon de-yasmi kayam if the father would still be alive,
הוי טוען ואמר Havi to'en ve-amar here's what he would claim. He
would say תלם אחד עשיתי לך. Telem echad asiti lecha.
Yeah, I conceded one furrow's length. I didn't concede the whole field.
Okay? So if he said right if you know if this basically
is the field that's being sold, right, if this is the field
we'll call it A, and basically and I say on the east
the field is bordered on the east by field B which is
by my field B, right, that's what the document says it's bordered
on the east by my field B and I signed off on
it. So how much of my field B is my field? Maybe
my field B means this is the field that's the field I
conceded. Who said I right the tiny little furrow, a tiny little
strip. That's the amount I was willing to concede was his. I
wasn't conceding the whole field B was his. He says on the
east it's bordered by my field, by my other field. Fine, I'll
that was your other field, that tiny little strip, not the whole
plot. So that's all that I conceded. I don't know. The point
is is that is that you know with trying to you know...
You're talking like five hundred acres of land?
I understand.
No, he's not selling the furrow, he's using that as a bound
border marker. All right, anyway. So that's what the father would have
said. Okay, you have to understand that bottom line he has he's
proven that it was that it was the father's field and the
only point
is because of a of an implicit admission. So we if and
it's possible to interpret that implicit admission otherwise and we can understand
other reasons he might have written that like we said before you
know so we we would interpret that generously.
So let's take a look. Unless he actually really sold it to
that other
guy.
Now you're
talking. How do you prove it's stolen by real estate? You know,
what do you do? You prove that Charlie came in with his
thugs and kicked me out? No, what you prove it's stolen is
it's really an absence of proof. You show that the field had
been registered to me, Charlie does not have a document of sale,
he doesn't have three years of חזקה, Chazaka, so that's proof that
it's stolen. It's really absence of proof that Charlie took possession of
it. Right, that's the way it works in real estate, if he
doesn't have that document of sale. So what Michael is saying is
actually correct. I could prove it's stolen, but it really wasn't stolen.
Really it was that Charlie did buy it, Charlie just lost the
document of sale, right? So it's important to appreciate that side of
it as well, that even if I've proven it's stolen, it's really
not black and white that it's stolen.
Okay, so didn't even getting off the ground if Charlie had been
there for three years. Exactly. Okay, in each of these cases.
Exactly. Or if he had a document of sale or anything like
that. Right. Okay. So
anyway, אי הוה אבון דייתמי קיים הוה אמר ee hava avun d'yasmei
kayam hava amar תל אחד עשיתי לך tel echad asiti lach fine.
So you know, yeah, I conceded field A was yours, but I
only conceded that tiny little strip of field A. אמר ליה, amar
lei, so Abaye said back to him, שפיר קאמרת. shafir ka'amart. You
know what? That's a good point. דאמר רבי יוחנן d'amar Rabi Yochanan
because Rabbi Yochanan says אם טען ואמר, im ta'an v'amar, if he
actually claims and says תל אחד עשיתי לך, tel echad asiti lach,
that I wasn't conceding the whole field, only one photo, נאמן, ne'eman,
he would be believed. שקלוה והבו להו לייתמי. shakluha v'havu lehu l'yasmei.
Okay, so basically they awarded the field back to the orphans.
יישר כח, yasher koach, good job. Then he said one thing though.
Yes, the orphans got the field back, but now at least you
have to give back, give
him, give Charlie back that strip. פה הויא רכבא דדיקלי. poh hava
richba d'diklei.
There was a
whole like, whatever, what's it called, a copse, what's it called when
you have trees, a copse, a cops, whatever, a copse of like
palm
trees. Okay, like a dense row, a whatever, anyway, that's what it
means, there was some like thicket, a dense row of palm trees
on it, and he didn't want to give him the strip because
it had all these palm trees on it. Okay, it was worth
$10,000 even the tiny little strip.
So אמר ליה, amar lei, so the אפוטרופוס apotropus said back to
Abaye, אי הוה אבון דייתמי קיים, ee hava avun d'yasmei kayam, had
the father been around, הוה טעין ואמר, hava ta'in v'amar, he would
say, חזרתי ולקחתיה הימנו. chazarti v'lakachtiha heimenu. After, yes, I conceded that
that strip was Charlie's, but afterwards I bought it back from him.
Okay, now of course that's a little bit bizarre. So where's your
bill of sale? Okay? But somehow because the whole thing is only
being proved to be Charlie's, it's not really proven, it's only because
of like my own admission that it was his, so we're very
willing to reinterpret that in a way that neutralizes what that meant.
Okay, it's a מודה במקצת. modeh b'miktzat. Well yeah, Rashi sort of
says it's like a פה שאסר. peh she'asar. Like I since I,
but okay, right, right. Tosafot says the only reason it works, Tosafot
is very bothered why it works. Once I've conceded that it was
his, how could I then say I bought it back? So Tosafot
says that the document really did not have validated witnesses. So in
theory you could have claimed that the whole document was a forgery
and that gave extra weight to my other claims. But okay, it's
not clear. So anyway, אמר ליה, amar lei, he said, שפיר קאמרת.
shafir ka'amart. You know what? That's a good point.
דאמר רבי יוחנן d'amar Rabi Yochanan because first Rabbi Yochanan said you
can claim that all you conceded to was this tiny strip. And
then Rabbi Yochanan says and if you then claim and said חזרתי
ולקחתיה הימנו, chazarti v'lakachtiha heimenu,
yes, I concede that strip was his and then I repurchased it
from him, נאמן, ne'eman, you'd also be believed. Okay, so you did
an excellent job. That was brilliant. And you were מכוון mechaven exactly
to what Rabbi Yochanan had said that you, it's possible to claim
as a way of winning in this case. אמר אביי, amar Abaye,
Abaye said, האי מאן דמוקים אפוטרופא, hai man d'mokim apotropa, if you're
ever going to appoint an אפוטרופוס apotropus exactly, if you're ever going
to appoint somebody to handle your affairs, לוקים כי האי, lokim ke'hai,
get a guy like this, דידע ליהפוכא בזכותא דייתמי, d'yada l'hafocha bizchuta
d'yasmei, he really knows how to argue in favor of the orphans.
You know, so Abaye was handing out his business cards. So anyway,
Tosafot is just left asking, why didn't we need this guy to
argue with? Because בית דין Beis Din always is supposed to make
the best argument for the orphans. So why did Abaye initially rule
against him and require this as a counter-argument? Why didn't Abaye make
this rule? So Tosafot says, you know what, Abaye actually forgot what
Rabbi Yochanan had said. And it wasn't until this guy made the
argument that Abaye said, oh yeah, תקא, taka, Rabbi Yochanan said you
can, if you say that you are believed, and he remembered because
of this argument.
I tell you, that's a whole profession called the, what do you
call it, like a טוען רבני. toen rabanai. Okay, because God forbid
we don't have lawyers, we just have טוענים. toanim.
And Tosafot said we'd rather argue that he forgot than be left
with an inexplicable
sort of silence.
Right, I mean, how is it that you're not defending the interests
of the orphans? Right.
I hear we have lawyers who are
especially plead before the Supreme Court in the United States. Yeah. I
think it's a specialty. A specialty. Right.
Yeah. Okay, so Mishnah says מי שהלך למדינת הים.
mi
shehalach l'medinat hayam.
All this stuff got gone overseas. Somebody went overseas. ואבדה דרך שדהו.
v'avda derech sadehu. And here's the story. I, right, we have these
big, have you guys ever, you know, I mean, we don't live
in, like, you know, in Kansas, right, but sometimes you're driving and
you know, you see these huge, huge wheat fields, right? So here
we go, we have like, you know, these hundreds of acres
of wheat fields, right? Now, let's say they're not all owned by
the same person. Right in the middle of all these hundreds of
acres here's the main road, okay? Whatever, I don't care if it's
the רשות הרבים, Reshus HaRabim, whatever. Here's the main road, here's these
hundreds of acres, here are the cars going by, when you're seeing
all the cows, right, when we get out to real nature. Somewhere
in here is Reuven's field. All these other fields are owned by
other people. Okay, now Reuven has a right of access to get
to his field. He has some type of a path and a
right of access to get to his field. Okay, but the thing
is that Reuven then went on an overseas journey for a few
years, he came back, in the interim, in the interim, nobody sees,
the path doesn't exist anymore.
Okay, and the this-way-is-still-the-path, it's all filled with corn, the path doesn't
exist anymore. Okay, so he basically says, give me back my, you
know, give me back my field. The only thing is is that
nobody remembers where that path was. Was this the path? Was this
the path? Was that the path? Nobody remembers where that path was,
or at least they claim they don't remember.
מי שהלך למדינת הים, mi shehalach l'medinat hayam,
he went overseas, ואבדה דרך שדהו, v'avda derech sadehu, and the path
to his field got lost. אדמון אומר ילך לו בקצרה. Admon omer
yelech lo b'ketzara.
So, fine, give him the shortest one, but he obviously knows he
does have one path here and he's entitled to one way of
getting in, so you gotta at least give him the shortest one.
Equally, equally short?
Let's say it's bordering...
Who knows? But the point is, you can't tell him... Now he
assumes, it really only makes sense if there's like one person that
owns all of these fields. Then Reuven comes to Shimon and says,
Shimon, you gotta give me my path. And Shimon says, which path?
Ah, you don't know, you don't know, I'm not giving it to
you. But you know that you owe me a path, so pick
one. You have the right to pick the shortest one, you know,
or the one that goes through the least whatever, you can choose,
but you gotta give me a path because you know you owe
me a path. That's what Admon says.
וחכמים אומרים, v'chachamim omrim, and the וחכמים v'chachamim say, no, if you
don't know what path is yours, יקנה לו דרך במאה מנה, yikneh
lo derech b'meah maneh, the guy could charge you a hundred thousand
dollars for a path, או יפרח באויר, o yifrach b'avir, or fly
in the air. Okay? Which means basically, I'm really sorry, get lost,
you have no rights and if he wants to charge you a
million dollars for a path, he's entitled, and if you say I
can't get to my field, then he can tell you that's not
my problem, that's not my problem how you're going to get to
your field. If you want, go ahead, learn how to
fly.
Yes, an inconceivable solution, to fly through the air.
Yes, thank you, I do know that, yes.
But it
behooves us to understand that we're talking about Jewish people and how
they get along with each other. Right. And you know, we go
into these abstract, marvelous discussions,
but these are two neighbors, they're businessmen, they're family, I don't care,
you call
them neighbors, they're businessmen, neighbors, you know, family, all you know, they
could even be relatives. This is the way they act with each
other.
Yeah, it would fall away in two seconds if your next door
neighbor knocked on your door and said oh, by the way, my
uncle had bought like half of your front yard and it really
belongs to me. All of your neighborly stuff would change in two
seconds.
All
right.
מאי טעמא mai ta'ama exactly.
I hear you. מאי טעמא דרבנן? mai ta'ama d'rabanan? What's the reason
of the Rabbis? שפיר קאמר אדמון, shapir ka'amar Admon, Admon is saying
well. All right? You know,
there is some path there that's mine, even if I can't prove
which one, you gotta give me something.
So, I mean, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav, כגון שהקיפוה ארבעה בני אדם מארבע רוחותיה. k'gon she'hekifuha arba'ah b'nei
adam m'arba ruchoteha. Ah, different people own all of these different fields.
This is owned by Shimon, this is owned by Levi, this is
owned by Yehuda, this is owned by whatever. So any one person
I bring to court, they say no, the path wasn't in my
field, it was in the other guy's field. So everybody... I can't
take anybody to court. Okay. אי הכי, ei hachi, says the Gemara,
if that's true, מאי טעמא דאדמון? mai ta'ama d'Admon? Then what's Admon's
claim? Then of course you're right, nobody... you can't prove that anybody
owes you the path. So אמר רבא, amar Rava, okay, we have
to find a middle case. בארבעה דאתו מכח ארבעה, b'arba'ah d'atu m'koach
arba'ah, if there are four separate owners of the four surrounding fields,
you know,
or בארבעה דאתו מכח חד, b'arba'ah d'atu m'koach chad, or there are
four separate owners that originated in one owner. It used to be
that all this stuff around here was Shimon's. But then Shimon sold
it all to four separate people. So now I go to court
and I say Shimon owed me a path... a path. All right,
but Shimon isn't around. Which of these four people do you want
to demand your path from? And I don't know which one of
them whose field it's in? So you can't bring any particular person
to court. So in that case everybody agrees that you've lost that
you're stuck. Okay. כולי עלמא
לא פליגי דמצי מדחי ליה kulei alma lo peligi dematzi madchei lei
that everybody you want to bring to court can say the path
wasn't in my yard, go prove the path was in my field.
כי פליגי אימת בדחד דאתי מכוח ארבע
ki peligi eimat bedchad deati
mikoch arba that it used to be that the four you know
that the four directions this you know were owned by four separate
people and then Shimon came and Shimon was one of those you
know mega corporations and bought up all the fields okay and they
were also trying to buy up my field okay and that's why
they were forcing me out or whatever okay so some big corporation
came and bought these up but these were all owned by separate
farmers okay but now my path is definitely in one of the
fields owned by this corporation so I should be able to bring
this doesn't have to be a corporation but I should be able
to bring this one person to court and say somewhere in those
fields that you bought up is my path you have to give
me a path okay that seems like a reasonable argument so כי
פליגי בדחד דאתי מכוח ארבע ki peligi bedchad deati mikoch arba Admon
סבר savar מכל מקום דרכי איכא גבך mikol makom darchai ika gabach
I don't care originally I didn't know whose field it was in
now I know that my path is in one of the fields
that you own ורבנן סברי verabbanan savrei and the rabbis hold אי
שתקת שתקת ei shatakt shatakt I can say back to you look
buddy shut up and it'll be in your best interest and we'll
make some deal I'll sell it to you on the cheap or
something like that but ואי לא vei lo if you want to
actually bring this to court then you're going to lose why are
you going to
lose מהדרנא שטרא למרייהו mehaderna shtra lemarihu I would just go ahead
and sell the field give the fields back to the people I
bought it
from ולא מצית לאשתעויי דינא בהדייהו velo matzit leishtauyei dina bahadeihu and
you won't be able to bring them to court because then because
they're four different owners and each owner will push you off to
the next and that's a very bizarre claim I have to tell
you because then I would say back fine you want to do
that go go sell it back to them like you know you're
not going to want to sell it back to them you wanted
the field for a particular reason you would lose out on the
whole transaction or whatever and it seems like I'm not really saying
that I'm going to sell it back it seems like what I'm
saying is since originally when it's like when you originally had that
path you know and when it was originally lost where it was
or whatever you could not win the court case then you don't
get more rights now just because I consolidated all the field okay
since it originated in a scenario in which you could not have
successfully you know sued for the recovery of your path yes
I was going to say it's like he's just guy squeezing him
you know it's not a reasonable response thanks yes I know right
okay so the Gemara says so if that's the scenario anyway I
think you have my sympathies are here with Admon not just because
my sympathies are with this poor guy that lost the path you
know but it's because like I just don't really get the argument
like oh you can't win now because it originated in a scenario
that you couldn't win fine but now I can win now you
have all the field so wait a
minute ההוא דאמר להו hahu deamar lehu somebody said said on his
deathbed to his children דקלא לברת dikla lebrat give this palm tree
to my daughter it was a deathbed bequest אזלו יתמי פלגו בנכסי
azlu yatmei palgu benichsei
the orphans the heirs of course the sons the men went and
they divided up the whole estate ולא יהבו לה דקלא velo yahu
lah dikla and they no they divided it without considering the fact
that she was entitled to a palm tree and now she's coming
and she wants her palm tree and every and
no one knows which palm tree it was
no he wasn't specific which one they had to pick a palm
tree give her a palm tree and they didn't do that they
divided it all up and now she's coming to court and she
says I want my palm tree and every one of her brothers
said no go to the other brother your palm tree's in his
in his property so
אזלו יתמי azlu yatmei okay דקלא סבר רב יוסף למימר היינו מתניתין
savar Rav Yosef lemeimar hainu matnitin that's our Mishna that everybody can
push her off just like all of these different owners of the
field can push you off to the other
owner so אמר ליה אביי amar lei Abaye Abaye said no מי
דמי mi dami you can't compare התם כל חד וחד מצי מדחי
ליה hatam kol chad vechad matzi madchei lei there everybody who owns
you know one some of the field can say your path was
never in my field right and I never you know so I'm
not your litigant at all your path was never in my
field הכא דקלא גבייהו hacha dikla gabaihu here there was no question
that the estate owed her a palm tree okay so there it
started with the fact that the estate owed her a palm tree
and therefore just because they divided the estate doesn't entitle them to
the fact right that they were that they that they that they
had to that they had to
do it now מאי תקנתיהו mai takantaihu so what should you do
ליהבו לה דקלא leihavu lah dikla so just reverse it all give
her a palm tree and you can give her the cheapest
one והדר וליפלגו מרישא vehadar velipalgu mereisha then go ahead and re-divide
the estate okay if you think that giving her the palm tree
makes it unfair why does one brother have to give and not
the other fine so just reverse it all but you have to
now part of the reason here also is it should be
said now But here the
problem, the point is also that it was a non-specific palm tree.
If the guy had said, right, give her you know give her
the following palm tree, I don't know, and he wrote it on
a piece of paper and which exactly palm tree he meant and
then the piece of paper was lost, let's say some scenario like
that, right, and then they divided the estate, maybe they could get
away with it because they could always say everyone could say this
isn't the specific palm tree that Dad was talking about. Right? So
part of the reason here why they remain obligated is because it
was never a specific one which you could say was in this
plot of land as opposed to that plot of land. It was
always that the estate had to ensure that she got a palm
tree and therefore that remains even after the estate is divided.
If I was attorney for this woman I'd say, get a palm
tree from each brother and then you'd never have to worry about
pulling back the land together.
Yeah, let's get the brothers to agree to that. All right. So
the גמרא says like
this: ההוא דאמר להו, Hahu d'amar lehu, somebody said to his heirs
right before he died,
דקלו לברת, diklu l'bras, give a palm tree to my daughter. Apparently
it was a thing. שכיב, shachiv, he died, שבק תרי פלגי דדיקלא.
shavak try palgei d'dikla. And he left over, like there was a
lot of individual palm trees and then there were two palm trees
that he had fifty percent ownership in. So the heirs would rather
give her the two palm trees of fifty percent ownership, which is
a much bigger pain in the neck dealing with a partner and
the whole thing, than one palm tree of a hundred percent ownership.
Okay and that's what they wanted to say that that would fulfill
the deathbed bequest. יתיב רב אשי וקקשיא ליה, yasiv Rav Ashi v'kakashya
lei, so רב אשי Rav Ashi was sitting and he was like,
you know, struggling with it. מי קרו אינשי לתרי פלגי דיקלא דיקלא,
mi karu inshi l'trei palgei dikla dikla, would people call two halves
of two palm trees a palm tree? או לא, o lo, or
not? אמר ליה רב מרדכי לרב אשי, amar lei Rav Mordechai l'Rav
Ashi, מרדכי Mordechai said to רב אשי... Rav Ashi... said to רב
אשי, Rav Ashi, הכי אמר אבימי מהגרוניא משמיה דרבא, hachi amar Avimi
me'Hagronya mishmei d'Rava, this is what אבימי Avimi מהגרוניא me'Hagronya said in
the name of רבא, Rava, קרו אינשי לתרי פלגי דיקלא דיקלא, karu
inshi l'trei palgei dikla dikla, yes, people would call two halves a
whole. And therefore they're entitled to give it to her because basically
since it's not specific what the father wanted, you know, she has
the upper hand is on the heirs and as long as they
can make a reasonable claim that this is fulfilling the deathbed wishes
of the, you know, deceased, then they're actually then they're discharging their
obligation. Okay, so what? Go on. No, I'm... I'm done. I didn't
actually prepare the next one but we could fake it.
No,
we're going to end because it's... I mean because the last דף
is also really long.